<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The petition of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament. Presented to His Majestie at Beverly the 16. of July 1642. With His Majesties answer thereunto.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09083</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922667</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80922667</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191872</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191872)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2893:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The petition of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament. Presented to His Majestie at Beverly the 16. of July 1642. With His Majesties answer thereunto.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"By the King. Our expresse pleasure is, that this our answer be read and published throughout all churches and chappels of the kingdome of England and dominion of Wales by the severall parsons, vicars, or curates of the same."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191872:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PETITION OF THE LORDS AND COMMONS Aſſembled in Parliament. Preſented to His MAJESTIE at <hi>Beverley</hi> the 16 of <hi>July</hi> 1642. With His MAJESTIES Anſwer thereunto.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="notice">
                        <p>By the King.</p>
                        <p>OUR expreſſe pleaſure is, That this Our Anſwer be read and publiſhed throughout all Churches and Chappels of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Wales,</hi> by the ſeverall Parſons, Vicars, or Curates of the ſame.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie. <hi>Anno</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:191872:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191872:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE HVMBLE PETITION Of the LORDS and COMMONS aſſembled in Parliament: Preſented to His Majeſtie at <hi>Beverley</hi> the 16. of <hi>July</hi> 1642.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Majeſtie,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough we, Your Majeſties moſt humble and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subjects, the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, have been very unhappy in many former. Petitions and Supplications to Your Majeſty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have repreſented our moſt dutifull Affections in adviſing and deſiring thoſe things which wee held moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the preſervation of Gods true Religion, Your Majeſties ſafety and Honour, and the peace of the Kingdome; And with much ſorrow do perceive, That Your Majeſty, incenſed by many falſe calumnies and ſlanders, doth continue to raiſe Forces againſt us, and Your other peaceable and loyall Subjects, and to make great preparations for War, both in the Kingdome, and from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas; And by Arms and Violence to over-rule the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and advice of Your great Councell; and by force to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Queſtions there depending, concerning the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Liberty of the Kingdome: Yet ſuch is our earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of diſcharging our dutie to Your Majeſty and the Kingdome, to preſerve the peace thereof, and to prevent the miſeries of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill War amongſt Your Subjects; That notwithſtanding we hold our ſelves bound to uſe all the means and power, which by the Lawes and Conſtitutions of this Kingdome wee are truſted with for defence and protection thereof, and of the Subjects from force and violence; We do in this our humble and loyall Petition, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate our ſelves at Your Majeſties feet; beſeeching Your Royall Majeſty, That You will be pleaſed to forbear, and remove all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations and actions of War, particularly, the Fores from about <hi>Hull,</hi> from <hi>Newcaſtle, Tinmouth, Lincoln,</hi> and <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> and all other places; And that your Majeſtie will recal the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Array, which are illegall, diſmiſſe Troops, and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Guards by You raiſed; That Your Majeſtie will come neerer to Your Parliament, and hearken to their faithfull advice
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191872:3"/>and humble Petitions, which ſhall onely tend to the defence and advancement of Religion, Your Own Royall Honour and Safety, the preſervation of our Lawes and Liberties: And we have been, and ſhall ever be carefull to prevent and puniſh all Tumults, and ſeditious Actions, Speeches, and Writings, which may give Your Majeſtie juſt cauſe of diſtaſte or apprehenſion of danger; from which publike aims and reſolutions, no ſiniſter or private reſpect ſhall ever make us to decline: That Your Majeſtie will leave de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents to the due courſe of Juſtice; And that nothing done or ſpoken in Parliament, or by any Perſon in purſuance of the command and direction of both Houſes of Parliament, bee que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned any where but in Parliament.</p>
            <p>And we, for our parts, ſhall be ready to lay down all thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations which wee have beene forced to make for our defence. And for the Town of <hi>Hull,</hi> and the Ordinance concerning the <hi>Militia;</hi> as we have in both theſe particulars, onely ſought the preſervation and peace of the Kingdome, and the defence of the Parliament from force, and violence, ſo we ſhall moſt willingly leave the town of <hi>Hull</hi> in the ſtate it was before Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> drew any Forces into it; delivering Your Majeſties Magazine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and ſupplying whatſoever hath been diſpoſed by us for the ſervice of the Kingdome: We ſhall be ready to ſettle the <hi>Militia</hi> by a Bill, in ſuch a way as ſhall be honorable and ſafe for Your Majeſty, moſt agreeable to the dutie of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and effectual for the good of the Kingdom; that the ſtrength thereof be not imployed againſt it ſelf; and that, which ought to be for our ſecurity, applyed to our deſtruction: and that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thoſe who profeſſe and deſire ſtill to preſerve the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, both in this Realm, and in <hi>Ireland,</hi> may not be left naked, and indefenſible, to the miſchievous deſignes, and cruell, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of thoſe who are the profeſt and confederated enemies thereof, in Your Majeſties dominions, and other neighbour-nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. To which, if Your Majeſties courſes and counſels ſhall from henceforth concur, we doubt not but we ſhall quickly make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the world, by the, moſt eminent effects of love and dutie, That Your Majeſties perſonall ſafety, Your Royall Honour and Greatneſſe are much dearer to us then our own lives and fortunes; which we do moſt heartily dedicate, and ſhall moſt willingly imploy for the ſupport and maintenance thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_petition">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:191872:3"/>
            <head>HIS MAJESTIES ANSWER To the aforeſaid PETITION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough His Majeſtie had no great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to beleeve, That the directions ſent to the Earle of <hi>Warwick,</hi> to go to the river of <hi>Humber,</hi> with as many Ships as He ſhould think fit, for all poſſible Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to Sir <hi>John Hotham;</hi> (whileſt His Majeſtie expected the giving up of the Town unto Him) and to carry away ſuch Arms from thence, as his diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thought fit to ſpare out of His Majeſties Own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazin; The chuſing a Generall by both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for the Defence of thoſe who have obeyed their Orders and Commands (be they never ſo extravagant and illegall;) Their Declaration, That in that Caſe, they would Live and Die with the Earle of Eſſex their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; (all which were Voted the ſame day with this Petition) and the Committing the Lord Major of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to Priſon for executing His Majeſties Writs and Lawfull Commands, were but ill Prologues to a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which might compoſe the miſerable diſtractions of the Kingdome; Yet, His Majeſties paſſionate deſire of the Peace of the Kingdome, together with the Preface
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191872:4"/>of the Preſenters, That they had brought a Petition full of Duty and Submiſſion to His Majeſtie, and which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired nothing of Him, but His conſent to Peace, which His Majeſtie conceived to bee the Languge of both Houſes too) begot a greedy hope and expectation in Him, That this Petition would have been ſuch an Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Peace, that it would at leaſt have ſatisfied His Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the eleventh of this Moneth, by delivering up <hi>Hull</hi> unto His Majeſtie. But to His unſpeakable grief, His Majeſtie hath too much cauſe to beleeve, That the end of ſome perſons, by this Petition, is not in truth, to give any reall ſatisfaction to His Majeſtie, but by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretences of making offers to Him, to Miſ-lead, and Seduce His People, and lay ſome imputation upon Him, of denying what is fit to be granted; otherwiſe, it would not have thrown thoſe unjuſt Reproaches and Scandalls upon His Majeſtie, for making neceſſary and juſt Defence for His Own Safetie, and ſo peremptorily juſtified ſuch Actions againſt Him, as by no rule of Law or Juſtice can admit the leaſt colour of defence; and after ſo many free and unlimited Acts of Grace paſſed by His Majeſtie, without any Condition, have propoſed ſuch things, which in Juſtice cannot be denyed to Him, upon ſuch Conditions, as, in Honour, He cannot Grant. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that all the world may ſee how willing His Majeſty would be to embrace any overture, that might beget a right underſtanding between Him and His two Houſes of Parliament, (with whom He is ſure He ſhall have no contention, when the private practices, and ſubtill inſinuations of ſome few Malignant Perſons ſhall bee diſcovered, which His Majeſtie will take care, ſhall bee ſpeedily done) He hath with great care weighed the particulars of this Petition, and returnes this Anſwer:</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:191872:4"/>
            <p>That the Petitioners were never unhappy in their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions or Supplications to His Majeſtie, whileſt they deſired any thing which was neceſſary or convenient for the preſervation of Gods true Religion, His Majeſties ſafety and honour, and the Peace of the Kingdome; and therefore when thoſe generall envious foundations are laid, His Majeſtie could wiſh ſome particular inſtances had been applyed. Let Envie and Malice object one particular Propoſition for the preſervation of Gods true Religion, which His Majeſtie hath refuſed to conſent to what Himſelf hath often made for the eaſe of tender conſciences, and for the Advancement of the Proteſtant Religion, is notorious by many of His Meſſages, and Declarations; what regard hath been to His Honour and ſafecy, when He hath been driven from ſome of His Houſes, and kept from other of His Towns by Force; and what care there hath been of the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome when endeavour hath been uſed to put all His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in Arms againſt Him, is ſo evident, that His Majeſtie is confident, He cannot ſuffer by thoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall imputations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tis enough that the world knowes what He hath granted, and what He hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed.</p>
            <p>For His Majeſties raiſing Forces, and making prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for War, (whatſoever the Petitioners, by the ill Acts of the Enemies to His Majeſties Perſon and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and by the calumnies and ſlanders raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt His Majeſtie by them, are induced to beleeve) all men may know, what is done that way is but in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to His Own Defence. Let the Petitioners remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber That (which all the world knowes) His Majeſtie was driven: from His Palace of <hi>White-hall</hi> for fafety of His Life; That both Houſe of Parliament, upon their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191872:5"/>own Authority, raiſed a Guard to themſelves, (having gotten the Command of all the Train-bands of <hi>London</hi> to that purpoſe) without the leaſt colour or ſhadow of Danger; That they uſurped a Power, by their pretended Ordinance, (againſt all principles and elements of Law) over the whole <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome, without and againſt His Majeſties Conſent; That they tooke Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of His Town, Fort, and Magazine of <hi>Hull,</hi> and committed the ſame to Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> who ſhut the Gates againſt His Majeſtie; and by force of Arms, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed entrance thither to His Own Perſon; That they ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified this Act, which they had not directed, and took Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> into their protection for whatſoever He had done, or ſhould do againſt His Majeſtie; And all this whilſt His Majeſtie had no other attendance, then His Own meniall Servants: Upon this, the duty and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of this County prompted His Subjects here to provide a ſmall Guard for His Own Perſon; which was no ſooner done, but a Vote ſuddenly paſſed of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties intention to levie War againſt His Parliament (which God knowes His Heart abhorreth) and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all His Majeſties Profeſſions Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Proteſtations to the contrary, ſeconded by the cleer Teſtimony of ſo great a number of Peers upon the place, Propoſitions and Orders for levies of Men, Horſe, and Arms were ſent throughout the Kingdome; Plate, and Money brought in, and received; Horſe, and Men raiſed towards an Army, muſtered, and under Command; and all this contrary to the Law, and to His Majeſties Proclamation: And a Declaration publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, That if He ſhould uſe force for the recovery of <hi>Hull,</hi> of ſuppreſſing the pretended Ordinance for the <hi>Militia,</hi> it ſhould be held levying War againſt the Parliament;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191872:5"/>and all this done before His Majeſtie granted any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, for the leavying, or raiſing a Man: His Majeſties Ships were taken from Him, and committed to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody of the Earle of <hi>Warwick,</hi> who preſumes, under that Power, to uſurp to himſelf the Soveraignty of the Sea; to chaſe, fright, and impriſon ſuch of His Majeſties good Subjects as deſire to obey His lawfull Commands, although He had notice of the legall Revocation of the Earle of <hi>Northumberlands</hi> Commiſſion of Admirall, whereby all Power derived from that Commiſſion cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Let all the world now judge who began this War, and upon whoſe account the miſeries which may follow muſt be caſt, what His Majeſtie could have done leſſe then He hath done; and whether He were not compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to make proviſion, both for the Defence of Himſelf and recovery of what is ſo violently, and injuriouſly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Him, and whether theſe Injuries, and Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities are not juſt grounds for His Majeſties Feares, and Apprehenſions of further miſchief and danger to Him: Whence the Feares and Jealouſies of the Petitioners have proceeded hath never been diſcovered, the dangers they have brought upon His good Subjects are too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; what thoſe are they have prevented, no man knowes: And therefore His Majeſtie cannot but look upon that charge, as the boldeſt, and the moſt ſcandalous hath been yet laid upon Him, That this neceſſary provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, made for his Own Safety and Defence, is to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the judgement and advice of his great Councell, and by force to determine the queſtions there depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, concerning the Government? and Liberty of the, Kingdome: If no other force had been raiſed, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine thoſe queſtions then by his Majeſtie, this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy miſ-underſtanding had not been: And his Majeſty
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191872:6"/>no longer deſires the Bleſſing, and Protection of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God upon Himſelf, and His Poſterity, then he and they ſhall ſolemnly obſerve the due execution of the Laws, in the defence of Parliaments, and the juſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome thereof.</p>
            <p>For the Forces about <hi>Hull,</hi> His Majeſtie will remove them, when He hath attained the end for which they were brought thither; when <hi>Hull</hi> ſhall be reduced again to His ſubjection, He will no longer have an Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; and when He ſhall be aſſured, That the ſame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and pretence of publike good, which took <hi>Hull</hi> from Him, may not put a Garriſon into <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to keep the ſame againſt Him, He will remove His from thence, and from <hi>Tinmouth;</hi> till when the example of <hi>Hull</hi> will not out of His memory.</p>
            <p>For the Commiſſions of Array, which are legall, and are ſo proved by a Declaration now in the Preſſe; His Majeſtie wonders why they ſhould at this time bee thought grievous, and fit to be recalled; If the feares of Invaſion and Rebellion be ſo great, that by an illegall pretended Ordinance it is neceſſary to put His Subjects into a poſture of defence, to Array, Traine, and Muſter them, He knows not why the ſame ſhould not be done in a Regular, Known, Lawfull way; but if in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Commiſſion any thing ſhall bee unlawfully impoſed upon His Subjects, His Majeſty will take all juſt and neceſſary care for their redreſſe.</p>
            <p>For His Majeſties coming nearer to His Parliament, His Majeſtie hath expreſſed Himſelf ſo fully in His ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Meſſages, Anſwers, and Declarations, and ſo parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly avowed a reall fear of His ſafety, upon ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as cannot bee anſwered, that He hath reaſon to take Himſelf ſome what neglecſted, That ſines upon ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191872:6"/>manifeſt reaſons, it is not ſafe for His Majeſtie to come to them, both His Houſes of Parliament will not come nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to His Majeſty, or to ſuch a Place, where the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Dignity of Parliament might bee preſerved. However His Majeſtie ſhall be very glad to hear of ſome ſuch example in their puniſhing the Tumults, (which He knowes not how to expect, when they have declared that they knew not of any Tumults, though the Houſe of Peeres deſired, both for the Dignity and Freedome of Parliament, that the Houſe of Commons would joyne with them in a Declaration againſt Tumults) which they refuſed (that is, neglected to do) and other ſeditious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Speeches, and Writings, as may take that appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of danger from Him: Though, when He remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the particular complaints Himſelf hath made of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes of that nature, and that in ſtead of inquiring out the Authors, neglect of examination hath been, when offer hath been made to both Houſes to produce the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, (as in that treaſonable Paper concerning the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>) and when he ſees every day Pamphlets publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt His Crown, and againſt Monarchy it ſelf, as the Obſervations upon His late Meſſages, Declarations, and Expreſſions, and ſome Declarations of their own, which give too great encouragement in that Argument to ill-affected perſons; His Majeſtie cannot with confidence entertain thoſe hopes which would be moſt welcome to Him.</p>
            <p>For the leaving Delinquents to the due courſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, His Majeſtie is moſt aſſured He hath been no ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to any ſuch; if the tediouſneſſe and delay in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the vaſt charge in Officers Fees, the keeping men under a generall Accuſation without tryall a whole year and more, and ſo allowing them no way for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191872:7"/>and vindication, have frighted men away from ſo chargeable and uncertain an attendance, the remedy is beſt provided where the diſeaſe grew. If the Law be the meaſure of Delinquency, none ſuch are within His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties protection: But if by Delinquents ſuch are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood who are made ſo by Vote, without any treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe upon any known or eſtabliſhed Law; If by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents thoſe nine Lords are underſtood, who are made Delinquents for obeying His Majeſties Summons to come to Him, after their ſtay there was neither ſafe nor honourable, by reaſon of the Tumults and other Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, and whoſe impeachment, He is confident, is the greateſt breach of priviledge that, before this Parliament, was ever offered to the Houſe of Peeres; If by Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents ſuch are underſtood, who refuſe to ſubmit to the pretended Ordinance of the <hi>Militia;</hi> to that of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie; or to any other which His Majeſty hath not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to; Such, who for the peace of the Kingdome, in an humble manner, prepare Petitions to Him, or to both Houſes, as His good Subjects of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Kent</hi> did, whileſt ſeditious ones, as that of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and other places, are allowed and cheriſhed; If by Delinquents ſuch are underſtood, who are called ſo, for publiſhing His Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations (as the Lord Major of <hi>London</hi>) or for reading his Meſſages and Declarations (as divers Miniſters about <hi>London</hi> and elſewhere) when thoſe againſt him are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed with all Care and Induſtry, to poyſon and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the loyalty and affection of his people; If by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents ſuch are underſtood, who have or ſhall lend his Majeſty money in the Univerſities, or in any other places; his Majeſty declares to all the world, that he will protect ſuch with his utmoſt power and ſtrength, and directs, That in theſe Caſes they ſubmit not to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191872:7"/>any Meſſengers or Warrants, it being no leſſe his duty to protect thoſe who are innocent, then to bring the guilty to condigne puniſhment; of both which the Law is to be judge: And if both houſes do think fit to make a Generall, and to raiſe an Army for defence of thoſe who obey their Orders and Commands, his Majeſty muſt not ſit ſtill, and ſuffer ſuch who ſubmit to his juſt power, and are ſolicitous for the Laws of the Land, to periſh and he undone, becauſe they are called Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents. And when they ſhall take upon them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with the attendance of thoſe who are called by his Majeſties Writ, whilſt the ſend them to Sea to rob his Majeſty of his Ships, or into the ſeverall Counties to put his Subjects in Arms againſt him, his Majeſty (who onely hath it) will not loſe the power to diſpence with them to attend his Own perſon, or to execute ſuch Offices as are neceſſary for the preſervation of himſelf and the Kingdome, but muſt protect them, though they are called Delinquents.</p>
            <p>For the manner of the proceeding againſt Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, his-Majeſty will proceed againſt thoſe who have no priviledge of Parliament, or in ſuch, Caſes where no priviledge is to be allowed, as he ſhall be adviſed by his learned Councell, and according to the known and unqueſtionable rules of the Law: it being unreaſonable, that he ſhould bee compelled to proceed againſt thoſe who have violated the known and undoubted Law on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before them who have directed ſuch violation.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid thus much to the particulars of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, though his Majeſty hath reaſon to complain, That ſince the ſending this Petition, they have beaten their Drums for Souldiers againſt him, armed their new Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall with a Power deſtructive to the Law and Liberty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191872:8"/>of the Subjects, and choſen a Generall of their horſe; his Majeſty out of his Princely Love, Tenderneſſe, and Compaſſion of his People, and deſire to preſerve the peace of the Kingdom, that the whole force and ſtrength of it may be united for the defence of it ſelf, and the relief of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (in whoſe behalf he conjures both his houſes of Parliament, as they will anſwer the contrary to Almighty God, his Majeſtie, to thoſe that truſt them, and to that bleeding miſerable Kingdome, that they ſuffer not any Moneyes granted and collected by Act of Parliament to be diverted, or imployed againſt his Majeſty, whileſt his Souldiers in that Kingdome, are ready to mutiny or periſh for want of pay, and the barbarous Rebels prevail by that encouragement) is graciouſly pleaſed once more, to propoſe and require:</p>
            <p>That his Town of <hi>Hull</hi> be immediately delivered up to him; which being done (though his Majeſty hath been provoked by unheard of Inſolencies of Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> ſince his burning and drowning the Countrey, in ſeizing his Wine and other Proviſions for his houſe, and ſcornfully uſing his Servant, whom he ſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them, ſaying, <hi>It came to him by Providence and he will keep it;</hi> And ſo refuſing to deliver it, with threats, if he or any other of his fellow-ſervants ſhould again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to <hi>Hull</hi> about it; and in taking and detaining Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners divers Gentlemen, and others, in their paſſage over the <hi>Humber</hi> into <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> about their neceſſary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and ſuch other indignities, as all Gentlemen muſt reſent in his Majeſties behalf) his Majeſtie, to ſhew his earneſt deſire of Peace (for which he will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with his Own honour) and how far he is from deſire of Revenge, will grant a free and generall Pardon all perſons within that Town.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:191872:8"/>
            <p>That his Majeſties Magazine taken from <hi>Hull,</hi> bee forthwith put into ſuch hands as he ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>That his Navie be forthwith delivered into ſuch hands as he hath directed for the government thereof, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining thereof after his Majeſties directions publiſhed and received to the contrary, and imploying his Ships a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in ſuch manner as they are now uſed, being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious high-treaſon in the Commanders of thoſe Ships.</p>
            <p>That all Arms, Levies, and Proviſions for a War, made by the Conſent of both houſes (by whoſe example his Majeſty hath been forced to make ſome preparations) be immediatly laid down, and the pretended Ordinance for the <hi>Militia,</hi> and all power of impoſing Lawes upon the Subject, without his Majeſties conſent, be diſavow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without which, the ſame pretence will remain to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame miſchiefs; all which his Majeſty may as lawfully demand, as to live; and can with no more Juſtice be denyed him, then his Life may be taken from him.</p>
            <p>Theſe being done, and the Parliament adjourned to a ſafe and ſecure place, his Majeſty promiſes, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, and bindes himſelf, by all his confidence and aſſurance in the affection of his people, that he will inſtantly, and moſt cheerfully, lay down all the force hee ſhall have raiſed, and diſcharge all his future and intended Levies, that there may be a generall face of Peace over the whole Kingdome, and will repair to them; And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that all differences may bee freely debated in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary way, whereby the Law may recover its due reverence, the Subject, his juſt Liberty, and Parliaments themſelves, their full vigour and eſtimation; and ſo the whole Kingdome a bleſſed Peace, Quiet, and Proſperity.</p>
            <p>If theſe Propoſitions ſhall be rejected, his Majeſty doubts not of the protection and aſſiſtance of Almighty
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191872:9"/>God, and the ready concurrence of his good Subjects, who can have no hope left them of enjoying their own long, if their King may be oppreſſed and ſpoyled, and muſt be remedileſſe. And though his Towns, his Ships, his Arms, and his Money be gotten and taken from him, He hath a good Cauſe left, and the hearts of his people, which, with Gods bleſſing, he doubts not, will recover all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the defence of the Liberty and Law of the Kingdome, the Dignity and Freedome of Parliament, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie and the Relief of bleeding and miſerable <hi>Ireland</hi> be equally precious to the Petitioners, as they are to his Majeſty (who will have no quarrell but in defence of theſe) there will be a cheerfull and ſpeedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to what his Majeſty hath now propoſed and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>And of this, his Majeſtie expects a full and poſitive Anſwer, by Wedneſday the 27. of his inſtant <hi>July:</hi> till when he will not make any attempt of force upon <hi>Hull;</hi> hoping in the Affection, Duty, and Loyalty of the Petitioners; and in the mean time expects, That no ſupply of Men be put into <hi>Hull,</hi> or any of his Majeſties goods taken from thence.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
